<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="access-control">
  <title>Access Control</title>

  <para>
    Access to hardware by unprivileged users is traditionally granted
    in two ways either by granting access to the <emphasis>special
    device file</emphasis> or allowing access through another process,
    using IPC acting on behalf of the user. HAL follows the latter
    model and uses the system-wide message bus (D-Bus) as the IPC
    mechanism. In addition, HAL has support for modifying the ACL's
    (access control lists) on a device file to grant/revoke access to
    users based on several criteria.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="access-control-device-file">
    <title>Device Files</title>
    <para>
      If HAL is built with <literal>--enable-acl-management</literal>
      (and also <literal>--enable-console-kit</literal>) then ACL's on
      device objects with the
      capability <literal>access_control</literal> are automatically
      managed according to the properties defined in
      <xref linkend="device-properties-access-control"/>. In addition,
      for this configuration, HAL ships with a device information file
      that merges this capability on device objects that are normally
      accessed by unprivileged users through the device file. This
      includes e.g. sound cards, webcams and other devices but
      excludes drives and volumes as the latter two are normally
      accessed by a user through mounting them into the file system.
    </para>
    <para>
      Currently this HAL device information file specifies that all
      local users (e.g. logged in at the system console) will gain
      access to such devices. This hard coded policy is subject to
      change in the future when the freedesktop.org PolicyKit project is
      will be an optional dependency of HAL.
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition, 3rd party packages can supply device information
      files to specify (via
      the <literal>access_control.grant_user</literal>
      and <literal>access_control.grant_group</literal> properties)
      that a given user or group should always have access to a device
      file. This is useful for system-wide software (such as AV
      streaming management) that runs as an unprivileged system
      user. This interface is supposed to be stable so 3rd party
      packages can depend on it.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="access-control-ipc">
    <title>D-Bus method calls</title>
    <para>
      If HAL is built without ConsoleKit support
      (e.g. without <literal>--enable-console-kit</literal>) access to
      the various D-Bus interfaces that provides mechanisms is only
      protected by the D-Bus security configuration files
      (e.g. using <literal>at_console</literal> to restrict to console
      user on Red Hat systems) and, in certain cases, restricted to
      the super user.
    </para>
    <para>
      If ConsoleKit support is enabled, access to D-Bus interfaces is
      currently hardcoded to only allow active users at the system
      console. This hard coded policy is subject to change in the
      future when the freedesktop.org PolicyKit project is will be an
      optional dependency of HAL.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>

